Guide to the Hegeman family papers 1988.004
Brooklyn Historical Society
Hegeman family papers
1809-1886
Brooklyn Historical Society
Hegeman, John L.
Hegeman, James
Hegeman family
Hegeman, Rem
1988.004
0.1 Linear Feet in 8 folders.
The Hegeman family papers document the daily lives, careers, property, financial concerns, and family matters of the Hegeman family of Brooklyn, 1809 to 1886.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Peter Vojta, date unknown.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into five series by type.
Biographical note
Rem, James, and John L. Hegeman were brothers who descended from early Dutch settlers who immigrated to New Amsterdam (now New York City). Rem Hegeman lived in the town of Flatbush, one of the original six towns of Brooklyn. His brother, John L. Hegeman lived in Melville, Long Island, N.Y. during the 1880s.
Related Materials
Henry Onderdonk papers (ARC.045)
Thomas Hegeman New Utrecht, New York Justice of the Peace papers (1973.127).
Adrian Hegeman wills (ARC.039)
Hegeman family photographs (V1980.005)
Old Brooklyn Families: Genealogies of the Hegeman, Holgersen, Joosten, Nagel, Polhemius, Rapalje, Remsen, Stryker, Vanderbilt, and Van Wyck families. Santa Barbara, Calif.: s.n., 1986. CS69.O45 1986
Scope and Contents
The Hegeman family papers document the daily lives, careers, property, financial concerns, and family matters of the Hegeman family of Brooklyn, 1809 to 1886. Included in the collection are certificates, correspondence, wills, receipts, bills of sale, property documents, printed material, and one newspaper clipping.
Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Correspondence; Flatbush (New York, N.Y.); Bills of sale; Wills; Families -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Tax records; Receipts (financial records); Certificates; Accounts -- New York (State) -- Long Island; Long Island (N.Y.) -- Genealogy; Long Island (N.Y.) -- Commerce; Long Island (N.Y.); Families -- New York (State) -- Long Island; Families -- New York (State); Families -- New York (State) -- Albany; Huntington (N.Y.); Hegeman, James; Hegeman family; Hegeman, Rem; Hegeman, John L.
- Series 1: Correspondence, 1838-1845; 6 items (Box A0043, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains handwritten correspondence, dating from 1838 to 1845, addressed to Rem Hegeman. Included in the series is a letter from James Hegeman telling of the death of his wife and an infant child, as well as letters from William Hegeman.
  - From John Carhart, 1838 October 1
    Carhart, of Arcadia, NY, writes of farm prices.
  - From William Carman, 1839 July 6
    Carman of Arcadia, NY writes to Hegeman at Flatbush of the death of Alletia Carman.
  - From James Hegeman, 1839 July 22
    Rem's brother James writes from Arcadia, NY of the death of Alethea.
  - From William Hegeman, 1840 February 10
    Rem's brother William writes from Albany, NY inquiring about a will.
  - From William Hegeman, 1840 April 26
    Rem's brother William writes from Port Gibson, NY.
  - From R. Hegeman, 1845 May 14
    R. Hegeman writes to Rem Hegeman, Sr. from Newark, NY.
- Series 2: Certificates, 1809-1878; 3 items (Box A0043, Folder 2)
  This series contains three certificates, 1809 to 1878. Included are two certificates of military appointment for Rem Hegeman, 1809 (as Sgt. in Lt. Col. Jeremiah M. Johnson's regiment) and 1815 (to the Independent Battalion Governor's Guards of 1st Brigade of NY State Militia, signed by John Ditmas); and a Kings County Surrogate Court certificate of administration for the estate of John Hegeman to Rem Hegeman, 1878.
- Series 3: Receipts, circa 1800-1850
  This series contains receipts, 1810 to 1884, and undated. Included are handwritten receipts, 1810 to 1842; tax receipts; receipts for bills and services; and funeral expense accounts and receipts.
  - Receipts and bills to John, James, and Rem Hegeman, 1810-1884 (Box A0043, Folder 3)
    Names include John Lefferts, William Stoothoff, H. Ditmas, Dr. J.L. Jabriskie, A. & J.Z. Lott, Gerrit Stryker, Henry B. Burrill, A. Van Dyke.
  - Tax bills to Rem Hegeman from the Town of Flatbush, 1855-1882 (Box A0043, Folder 4)
  - Account of estate of James Hegeman, 1879 January 14 (Box A0043, Folder 5)
  - John L. Hegeman Huntington, L.I. receipts, 1883-1884 (Box A0043, Folder 6)
- Series 4: Property documents, 1847-1886; 2 items (Box A0043, Folder 7)
  This series contains two documents including the will of John Hegeman, 1847; and a bill of sale for a market wagon, 1886.
- Series 5: Printed materials, 1832-1879; 3 items (Box A0043, Folder 8)
  This series contains two volumes of The Daily Verse Expositor, No. 4 and 5, printed in 1832; and a news clipping from The Sun, January 4, 1879.